These days when you're building apps
with Ruby on Rails, more times than not,
you need to integrate with the AI
providers like OpenAI, the makers of
ChatgBT or Anthropic, the makers of
Claude. You know, bringing in these
integrations into your Rails app enables
you to build AI powered features like,
you know, generating content, generating
text, responding to prompts or
instructions from the users. There's so
many different possibilities. Frankly,
these are like essential features in
today's products and software being
built. So, I want to make this video to
show how I go about integrating with
OpenAI and Anthropic in all of the Rails
apps that I build. And of course, I
turned these into two new components
that I've added to instrumental
components to make it really fast and
really easy to get up and running with
an OpenAI integration and a Cloud
integration in your Rails app. So, let's
get right into it. and I'm going to show
you how you can fire this up really
fast. So, I have spun up a new Rails
app. I used some of the generators that
come with instrumental components to to
get here a fresh Rails app. I've got
authentication and some account stuff
built in. But in this video, I just want
to show you how I can generate and
install two new components which will
give us two integrations. One with
OpenAI and the other with Claude or
Anthropic if you will. Now, of course,
in this video, I am showing my
components library, instrumental
components, which you can learn more
about at
instrumental.dev, and that is what is
actually powering the generators that
I'm going to use to install the OpenAI
and Anthropic integrations. But I am
going to show you under the hood and
show you the codebase to show you what
these generators actually place into
your Rails application code so that you
can see how it all works. Okay. And I'm
going to start with the OpenAI
integration. I'll run rails g
instrumental open aai. And as always,
that's going to give us like an overview
of what's about to be installed. So I'm
going to proceed with this. So for this
integration, we are adding an
initializer, a couple of controllers, a
service, actually one controller, a
service class, and some views. So So
that's all set. And here is the recap.
Again, we have those files added to our
project. We are going to be making use
of the Ruby OpenAI gem that has been
automatically added to our gem file and
we added some routes for the example
implementation. Also, we have some some
localization stuff now built into all
the components with instrumental
components. Okay, so that is all set.
Let's run bundle to get that gem
installed. Now, in order for this to
work, we are going to need to connect to
our OpenAI account using the OpenAI API
credentials. So, in order to do that, we
need to add some credentials to our to
our Rails credentials file. So, I have a
shortcut to open up my credentials. And
in the docs on instrumental components,
you can go into the AI docs here. I'm
going to go into OpenAI. And we've
already run the generator. Now, this is
what we're going to need to add into our
credentials. And it's going to need an
access token like our API key and the
organization ID. So you can get those
from your OpenAI account. I believe it's
at
platform.openai.com. Now you're going to
need to get your credentials from your
OpenAI account. So you can, you know,
sign up for an account over there. Get
your credentials there and then drop
them in here. I'm going to do that now
off camera and then I'll close this out.
Okay. So I've saved that and the next
step is we need to go to the OpenAI
initializer. So, one of the files that
was just installed with this generator
was this initializer, and that's what
pulls in those API keys that we've saved
in credentials. All we need to do here
is uncomment the code that's all ready
for you and ready to go. Now, what did
this actually install aside from the
initializer? Well, let's look at our
application. Number one is in services.
We have this OpenAI service. This is
essentially the new tool that you now
have in your Rails application that you
can use to interact with the OpenAI API.
It's it's pretty flexible. You can, you
know, send it a prompt along with
several options like the system message,
system instructions, which model you
want to use, some max tokens, bunch of
other options here, parameters if you
will, like temperature and some other
stuff. And then it's going to respond
with the response or like the generated
response from the LLM. You know, we've
got several models available. As you're
working with this and as they're
releasing more models, you can of course
add to this array and keep this updated.
And we at Instrumental Components, by
we, I probably mean me. I'm going to be
keeping this up to date as well. Okay,
so this is the service object, the
service class that we're going to be
using whenever we're interacting with
it. But to make this even easier, this
component comes with an example
implementation. So you will find under
controllers, we now have OpenAI prompt
controller. And in views, we have OpenAI
prompt. We also added some routes right
here. OpenAI prompt. So let's go ahead
and start our server. I have a shortcut
for that. And I'm going to need to log
back in that uses our authentication
component. Okay. So now I'm in. Now we
can get to our open AI prompt at this
route. And you know what? I'm going to
actually add a navigation link to my
main navigation to make that easier. So
this uses our navigation layout that's
in that comes included with
instrumental. Let's see. Yeah, I think
that's it. Yep. Okay. So we have the
OpenAI prompt feature. This isn't, you
know, this is just a very basic
implementation. All it does is it lets
you type in instructions, anything that
you want. And then we have some optional
additional fields here. You can, you
know, put in some system instructions or
the advanced options as well. You know,
selecting which model you want to use,
max tokens, temperature, and whatnot.
So, this is really just like an example
imple implementation so that you can see
what's going to happen. Let's actually
just go ahead and try it out. Tell me a
joke. generate response. And this
actually uses a Rails turbo response.
And just like that, we have why don't
scientists trust atoms? Because they
make everything
up. Well done. So, you know, it's also
spinning back some usage details. It
tells me what my prompt was. And in this
case, I did not give it any system
instructions. You know, you can do
things like, tell me a joke. Everything
you say should be in
Spanish. Let's generate that again. And
there you go. I don't even really speak
Spanish so well, but something about
Facebook and Twitter there. Maybe you
can tell me in the comments what that
actually says. So, this again is just
like an example implementation, and you
can check it out by going into that
controller. And you can see when we
create a new response, we are opening up
a new instance of the OpenAI service and
then we're sending it the prompt and
then we're sending it whatever options
we put into the form and then it's
getting the response, sending it back
and we are rendering that with a turbo
stream. So let me show you another
example of how we can actually use this
in our application. I'm going to show
you a little bit of like building out a
new feature that might use the OpenAI
integration. So, let's go ahead and
scaffold out a new model in our app,
just a posts model, like a blog post
model. I'm going to go ahead and stop
the server. You can use a regular Rails
scaffold, but I'm going to use the
instrumental Rails scaffold, which is
like a scaffold on steroids. We have I
have another whole video that covered
that in depth. So, here we go. I'm going
to do Rails G instrumental scaffold. And
let's call it post. And we'll give each
post a title. We're going to keep it
super simple. I could add like a lot
more attributes here, but I'm just going
to do posts and titles. And later on we
can add like rich text and all that kind
of stuff, but this is just an example.
Okay. So, we are going to install. We're
actually using the scaffolds component
to install a uh a post. And we have some
questions here to configure our new post
that's being generated. Again, my other
video on the instrumental scaffolding
system goes into this stuff in depth,
but you can sort of see what's going on
here. And we also has have a fast mode
for instrumental components which would
run through this like instantly. So, I
really probably should should enable
that on the next run. Okay, so we have
set up our posts model. Got a bunch of
bunch of views and controllers and some
routes. And we also added a migration.
So, let's do rails db migrate. Let's go
back to our navigation and add it into
our navigation as well. Let's let's put
it up here. Post path. I think that
should work. Let's see. Oh, I have to
actually start the server. Okay, so
we've just scaffolded out this basic
posts path. Hello world. I'm a post.
Great. So, I just created a post. All it
has is a title and a slug. Now, that
obviously did not use AI. So, how can we
AIify the post model a little bit? This
is just a madeup example. But let's
imagine we want to set up a system where
every time we create a new post, we use
AI to rewrite the title of the post and
make it a silly rhyme or something,
right? I'm just making stuff up as I go
along here. So, I'm going to go ahead
and come back in here. I'm going to go
to my post model and we want to after
create we want to
rewrite title and then we're going to
define that. Now, obviously, I could
it's it's already suggesting the OpenAI
service, but I'm going to kind of show
you a little bit of vibe coding here to
I what I really want to demonstrate is
how well instrumental components and
Ruby on Rails in general works with vibe
coding or using AI or prompting AI in a
tool like cursor because it's really
just Rails stuff. Like a service class
is just Rails stuff. So, I can do this.
I can just highlight this empty method
here and go into my AI chat and say I
want
this call back to rewrite the title of
the new post by turning it in into a
funny rhyme. Oops. And then I'm going to
instruct it to use our
existing open AI
service. So, you know, cloud force
sonnet is going to be smart enough to
find that file in our codebase and then
it's going to use that file to build out
the functionality. So, let's go ahead
and get that going. Okay, so it filled
out our our callback method here. I'm
going to accept that and we can see what
it did. We'll close up the chat here.
So, it created this prompt like take
this title, the title that the post
initially has, rewrite it as a funny,
catchy rhyme, keep it short and snappy,
return only the rhyming title and
nothing else. So, you know, cursor and
claude just came up with this, which is
exactly what I wanted. It also added
some system instructions. You are a
creative writer who specializes in. All
right. So, then we are opening up the
open AI service which calls it here. We
are sending it the prompt and we're
sending it the system instructions and
these options for temperature and max
tokens. Then we have a response and
we're going to update the title on the
post. Okay, so let's try it out. I'm
going to get this. I'm going to create a
new
post. Post about
baseball. Let's see what it comes up
with. It called it batting banter, a
ball game blabber. I don't even know
what that means, but as you can see, it
came up with something, right? So, I'm
not going to say that this is the like
the killer app of the year, but it just
goes to show how you can start to
integrate AI into your app. Now, that's
using the OpenAI API, but of course, the
Claude API from Anthropic is just as
popular, if not more popular when it
comes to AI integration. So, we have
another component from instrumental
components. It works almost exactly the
same except it integrates with the
anthropic API instead. So let's just get
that installed just to show you how that
works. All right. So I'm going to stop
this. We're essentially going to do
exactly what we did before. We're going
to do rails g instrumental and this time
anthropic. And I'm going to also use the
fast flag to make this go a lot faster
this time. So we are going to install
the anthropic component. I want to
proceed with that. And that's all done.
So again, it looks very similar. You can
see that we have an initializer for
anthropic, anthropic prompt controller,
anthropic service. Okay, so we're going
to and we did add the Ruby anthropic gem
and we're going to bundle this up. And
once again, I'm going to open my Rails
credentials and add my anthropic API key
into there. So I'm going to do that off
camera. Okay, I saved my Anthropic API
key, which I got from my Anthropic
account. And I'm also going to go into
Anthropic RB. That's the new file that
was added under initializers. Same deal.
Just need to uncomment that. And that is
good to go. And so now, and again, we
can just see, you know, the new stuff
that has been added. Again, just like we
added the anthropic the OpenAI
interface, now we have a very similar
anthropic interface to use as a nice
example. Let's go ahead and go to the
navigation and just add an easy link to
it and let's start the server. Okay, so
now we have anthropic prompt. I'm going
to go here. It literally works exactly
the same way except we're using clawed
models instead of OpenAI. And you know,
we're going to be adding the latest
models to this as we go along, but
again, we can just go ahead and tell a
funny joke. And there you go. Here is
Claude's response. It's a little bit
more verbose here, but you know, all the
same information. It just, you know,
serves as a good example for you. So,
overall, I think that that gives you a
look at how you can get these popular AI
LLMs integrated into your Rails
applications with these easy components
from instrumental components. Now, if
you found this helpful and if you want
to learn more about instrumental
components, I have a number of other
videos. The one I want to point you to
actually next is our commerce component
that will install a stripe integration
so that you can charge for your SAS
application, charge customers to use it,
especially if you are using AI
integrations which are going to cost you
money as the business owner. They, you
know, they use your tokens from your
OpenAI and your anthropic account. So,
you know, you don't want to necessarily
just, you know, launch these free
applications and let people draw down on
your tokens. So, you'll want to charge
customers to use your SAS. And to do
that, you will probably need to use the
commerce component from instrumental
components. I've got a deep dive video
on that. If you have any questions or
any requests for future videos, I'm
going to be doing a lot more videos on
using Cursor to build with AI and some
new workflows on building software much
faster. I'm excited to get into that.
But yeah, thank you for watching.